ELISENDA ORTIZ

Data Scientist

@ elisendaortiz@gmail.com

github.com/elisendaortiz

in Elisenda Ortiz



Data Scientist/ Mathematical Modeller

VesselsValue Ltd

Jan 2023 - Present, UK

VesselsValue Ltd is a leading supplier of financial and technical data to the maritime and aviation industries. As a Mathematical Modeller, I use statistics and machine learning to conduct research and development of new valuation models. I work closely with commercial staff, software developers and data analysts to design data products that meet the needs of a sophisticated client base. My main responsibilities include:

- · Conduct feasibility analysis considering data requirements
- Model design and performance evaluation
- Prototype deliverable products
- Project planning and team alignment
- Maintain internal technical documentation

Data Science Fellow

S2DS - Pivigo

July 2022 - Aug 2022, UK (remote)

In this role, I worked within a small team on developing a data-driven classification algorithm for vessels stoppages for our UK-based client VesselsValue Ltd. Tasks included:

- Creating a data cleaning ML pipeline in a collaborative fashion through the use of git.
- Carrying out exploratory data analysis and feature engineering while growing domain knowledge.
- Developing a Neural network classifier and conducting performance bench-marking.
- Setting actionable goals and adjusting priorities fast to deliver a viable product in 5 weeks.



MOST PROUD OF



Awards

Highest grade of Excellent *Cum Laude* for PhD thesis. Won two pre-doctoral scholarships for two separate PhDs.



Collaboration

Managed successful collaborations with international teams overcoming challenging time-zone differences and boosting remote work culture.



Project management

Exceptional time administration and communication skills. Enjoy owning the full life-cycle of a project, removing obstacles and meeting objectives.



Publications: Google scholar 3/6 first author.

EDUCATION

PhD in Physics of Complex Networks University of Barcelona, Spain, 2022

PhD in Computer Science*
Victoria University, New Zealand, 2017
*Voluntary withdrawal

MSc in Advanced Physics University of Barcelona, 2016

Course designer - Physics

Gauss online

May 2021 - July 2022, Philippines (remote)

Gauss online is a virtual academy offering bachelor students of STEM disciplines support in mathematics and physics via video-tutoring. In this role, I lead the design, documentation and content creation of a freshly started Physics division. I became proficient at communicating complex ideas and processes adjusting to a range of levels. I also supervised the accuracy of knowledge transfer at different stages from raw lessons until the final video-product.

Assistant teacher - Computational Physics

University of Barcelona

Sep 2018 - June 2019, Barcelona

Provided critical guidance to undergraduate students with zero prior coding experience on how to approach and solve practical coding assignments in Fortran. Also developed a private semi-automated system for faster marking.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming languages

- Python (advanced)
- Fortran (advanced)
- C++ (basic)
- Bash (basic)
- SQL (ongoing)

Data handling

Pandas, Numpy, Scikit-learn, Scipy, Networkx, Sympy, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Jupyter.

Machine learning

EDA, data visualization, regression, classification (logistic, random forest, SVM, Naive Bayes), clustering, neural networks, social networks, embedding, topic modeling, Agent Based simulations.

Mathematics

statistical analysis, probability, stochastic processes, non-linear dynamics, graph theory.

Software & tools

Git, ssh, virtual environments, cluster computing, Linux.

STRENGTHS

Resourceful Creative Hard-working

Eye for detail Proactive Confident

LANGUAGES

English	••••
Spanish	••••
Catalan	••••
Japanese	••••
Tagalog	•••••

HOBBIES

Tropical plants Aviation Kitesurfing
Sailing Motorcycle roadtrips Sunsets
Traveling

Elisenda Ortiz

PHD IN PHYSICS · COMPLEX NETWORKS

University of Barcelona, Department of Condensed Matter Physics & UBICS

Education _____

PhD in Physics Spain

UNIVERSITY OF BARCELONAMay 2017 - Jan 2022
Thesis: Mapping complexity through network geometry: from structure to dynamics of real-world networks

Advisor: Prof. M.Ángeles Serrano Grade: Excellent Cum Laude

PhD in Computer Science*

New Zealand

2016 - 2017

VICTORIA UNIVERSITY OF WELLINGTON

Thesis: *The emergence of barter: a complex systems study*Advisors: Dr. Marcus Frean and Prof. Stephen Marsland

*Voluntary withdrawal

Master in Advanced PhysicsSpainUNIVERSITY OF BARCELONA2014 - 2016

Specialization in computational methods and statistical physics. Thesis: *Navigability of the Internet as a time-varying complex network*

Advisor: Prof. M.Ángeles Serrano

Grade: 8.7/10

Bachelor of Physics Spain

University of Barcelona 2009 - 2014

Thesis: Disorder-induced critical phenomena in the 2D random-field Ising model

Advisor: Prof. Carmen Miguel

Grade: 10/10

Professional Experience _____

2023 -Now	Data Scientist/ Mathematical modeller, VesselsValue Ltd., UK
2022-2022	Data Scientist, S2SD - Pivigo, UK (remote)
2021-2022	Course Designer: Physics, Gauss Online, Philippines (remote)
2018-2019	Graduate Teaching assistant, University of Barcelona, Spain
2018-2019	Research Collaboration: Complexity72h, Scuola IMT Alti Studi Lucca, Italy
2016-2018	Research Collaboration: Topic modeling, Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand
2016-2016	Research assistant, Dept. of Fundamental Physics, University of Barcelona, Spain
2014-2016	Secretary & outreach coordinator, Institute of Cosmos Sciences, University of Barcelona, Spain

Awards, Fellowships, & Grants _

2022	PhD	Thesis Excellen	t Cum	Laude,	University	of Barcelona
------	-----	-----------------	-------	--------	------------	--------------

- 2020 **Tuition scholarship***, SCSS, Santa Fe Institute USA, *Unrealized due to COVID19
- 2020 Mobility grant, Ajuts de mobilitat al personal investigador UB, University of Barcelona
- 2019 **PhD Scholarship:**, APIF, University of Barcelona
- 2018 Project grant, Mapping Big Data Systems (Predoctoral co-investigator), Fundación BBVA
- 2016 PhD Scholarship, Te Pūnaha Matatini Reserach Center, New Zealand
- 2014 Honors Graduate thesis, University of Barcelona

Teaching	Experience				
2021 - 2022 2021 - 2022	Mechanics: Advanced, Curriculum designer Mechanics: Fundamentals, Curriculum designer	Gauss Online Gauss Online University of			
2018 - 2019	9 Computational Physics , Teaching Assistant				
Committees & Panels					
2018-2022 2017 2016-2017	PhD candidates committee, University of Barcelona Institute of Complex Systems (UBICS) Organizing committee Macfang conference, University of Barcelona Te Pūnaha Matatini Whānau committee, Victoria University of Wellington	Spain Spain New Zealand			
Publicati	ons				

PUBLISHED

- E. Ortiz, M.Á. Serrano, Multiscale voter model on real networks, Chaos, Solitons & Fractals, 165, 112847s (2021).
- **E. Ortiz**, G. García-Pérez, M.Á. Serrano, *Geometric detection of hierarchical backbones in real networks*, Physical Review Research, 2, 033519 (2020).
- M. Starnini, **E. Ortiz**, M.Á. Serrano *Geometric randomization of real networks with prescribed degree sequence*, New Journal of Physics, 21, 053039 (2019).
- B. Curran, K. Higham, **E. Ortiz**, D. Vasques, *Look who's talking: bipartite networks as representations of a topic model of New Zealand parliamentary speeches*, PLOS ONE, doi.10.1371 (2018).
- E. Ortiz, M. Starnini, M.Á. Serrano, Navigability of temporal networks in hyperbolic space, Scientific Reports, 7, 15054 (2017).

PREPRINTS

S. Chakraborty, X.R.Hoffmann, M.G. Leguia, F. Nolet, **E. Ortiz**, O. Prunas, L. Zavojanni, E. Valdano, C. Poletto, *Dynamics of new strain emergence on a temporal network*, arXiv:1805.04343 [physics.soc-ph] (2018).

Courses & Schools -

Feb 2021. Minicurs d'Introducció a la intel.ligència artificial, UBICS (online), Barcelona.

Dec 2019. Tutorial: Wikimedia public (Research) Resources, Lisbon, Portugal.

Jan 2019. Fractals and Scaling, Santa Fe Institute (online) USA.

Oct 2018. Entrepreneurship course, Institute for professional development (ICE), Barcelona.

May 2018. Workshop: Complexity72h, Lucca, Italy.

April 2018. Workshop: Membrane Computing, University of Barcelona, Barcelona.

Dec 2016. Workshop: Computation skills with Python, Te Punaha Matatini Hui, Wellington, New Zealand.

Aug 2016. Te Punaha Matatini Boot-Camp, Leigh, New Zealand.

Talks & Conferences _

Dec 2021. Complex Networks 2021, (online), Madrid.

Talk: Multiscale opinion dynamics on real networks.

Oct 2021. SICC Talks on Complexity, 16th SICC International Tutorial Workshop: Topics in nonlinear dynamics (online), Italy.

Jun 2021. Opinion Dynamics on Sheaves, BGSMath Colloquium (online), Barcelona.

Dec 2019. Complex Networks and their Applications, Lisbon, Portugal

Talk: Geometric randomization of real-world networks.

Sep 2019. Physics Challenges for Machine Learning and Network Science, Queen Mary University of London, UK. **Poster.**

Mar 2019. Complenet 2019, Tarragona, Spain.

Talk: Geometric randomization of real networks with prescribed degree sequence.

Jun 2018. UBICS day, Barcelona, Spain.

Jun 2018. NetSci 2018, Paris, France.

Talk: The navigability of temporal networks in hyperbolic space.

May 2018. Jornades Complexitat, Barcelona, Spain.

Poster

Nov 2017. Macfang: Mapping Complexity Foundations and Applications of Network Geometry, Barcelona, Spain. **Talk:** Navigating temporal networks in hyperbolic space.

Jun 2017. UBICS Founding Symposium, Barcelona, Spain.

Poster

May 2017. Jornades Complexitat, Castelldefels, Spain.

Poster

Dec 2016. Te Punaha Matatini Hui, Wellington, New Zealand.

Talk: Decentralised bilateral exchange in economic complex networks.

Nov 2016. Complex Economic & Social Systems Theme meeting, Auckland, New Zealand.